Okay,
welcome everyone. Uh, thanks for
attending today the active inference
institutees te textbook reading group.
It is October 2nd uh doing the relative
to the western hemisphere the evening
session of the textbook reading group.
This is cohort 9 reading chapter five of
the textbook. So, we're wrapping up uh
essentially the first half of the book,
and this chapter is a bit of an outlier
relative to what we've seen so far. It
does follow from and connect to the
preceding chapters, but it's here that
we get much more deeply into I would say
the more or less kind of like
neurobiological underpinnings of active
inference beyond just looking at notions
of generative models and free energy as
kind of a formalism involving gradient
descent and um sort of basian statistics
and mechanics. um
you know it comes into question well you
know this this is all much of this is
derived from neuroscience and so um even
though we get a lot of these cognitive
concepts of perception and action and uh
and the rest sensory attenuation it's
here that we start to see something much
closer to uh an understanding of maybe
how neuronal populations
communicate with one another what these
message passing schemes
excuse me, all about. So this um this
chapter begins with an interesting quote
uh from Rulo Lenus,
Colombian neuroscientist
uh quite a reputation behind him has
worked with uh NI NYU School of
Medicine. Uh basically there are two
types of animals. Animals and animals
that have no brains. They are called
plants. They don't need a nervous system
because they don't move actively. They
don't pull up their roots and run into
forest fire. Anything that moves
actively requires a nervous system.
Otherwise, it would come to a quick
death.
It's a very interesting way of opening
up this chapter. And from my personal
point of view, I think it is emphasizing
the significance of having a nervous
system and sort of neuronal
communication happening within an
organism. Um that said, using the active
inference framework, one could
nonetheless model uh in fact a plant
whether it be in the midst of a forest
fire or not. Um that depends on how you
want to draw the marov bank blanket.
What are the statistical boundaries
separating the plant from the not plant
or environment around it and what are
the sort of inputs or observations uh
received by the plant versus what are
its outputs. Uh so we as humans know
it's very important to us to have plants
for uh you know successful production of
oxygen. uh so they do have outputs and
there are different things that happen
that lead to plants being able to
persist or not. Uh so yeah I I find this
quote very interesting but I I think
that there need to be a few asterisks
after it um maybe to kind of understand
it and situate it here. Nonetheless, the
kind of the the broader theme beyond
just neurobiology is understanding
active inference and its attendant
process theory or neuronal process
theory. Um we know that the the free
energy principle is a principle. Um so
here a process theory refers to how
principles like the free energy
principle might be implemented in
certain systems like the brain and this
allows us to develop hypotheses
answerable to empirical data and further
produces a dialogue between say
technical audiences like engineers or
data scientists uh as well as
neurobiologists
uh cognitive scientists uh essentially
kind of um kind of producing the
dialogue that allows us to look at these
math complex mathematical formulisms,
look at empirical data uh and and what
we know about the brain and seeing where
these two things match up. Um in active
inference the basian belief updating
we've covered so far chapters 1 through
four may be carried out via here basian
message passing for there are different
kind of algorithms or forms that message
passing can occur. Um all the ones in
active inference we look at is be in the
kind of variational category um uh one
that's very commonly used is uh marginal
message passing is what it's called.
There's a nice paper on that by Par and
Fristen and others for 2019
um where marginal message passing is
kind of takes the best of both world
worlds as it were from variational
message passing which at times can sort
of lead to um overconfidence in its
outputs um versus belief propagation
which uh those who engage in data
science are um often well aware ware of
and it's uh the issue with belief
propagation is just that it's it's very
computationally demanding um and may
lead to intractability problems and so
we know from reading prior chapters um a
big part of active inference and the
free energy principle involves these
variational methods allow for overcoming
those kinds of hurdles.
So um I would recommend uh you know
further reading for those who are
interested in the kind of the
specificities of different kinds of
message passing. Um but here we'll just
we'll just kind of focus on um kind of
the way that these things are described.
Um message passing what is that? Um
neurons pass messages to one another? Do
all me do all neurons pass messages to
all other neurons? that is are they all
fully connected up to one another? Uh
absolutely not. Uh there there's much
more sparity sparse connectivity in the
brain. Certain neurons connect to
certain other neurons for those familiar
with Hebian learning and synapses. There
are neurons who were never communicating
with one another who then start to
communicate with one another based on
their relative activity and who they're
connected to. Um, and so whenever we do
the these kinds of, you know, neuroiming
experiments or or or try to create an
active inference model of these things,
of course, we're we're we're typically
not trying to model billions and
billions of neurons. We're trying to um
collect information for neuroiming and
empirical data. We're collecting uh kind
of signals from entire populations or
congregations of neurons that are
supposed to be more or less within
certain areas of the brain. So if you're
looking at like um you know the left
temporal lobe uh then then you're you're
commonly like for EEG you're putting an
electrode there and there's a a singular
signal and you're assuming that that
more or less is a proxy for all the
communication going on somewhere within
that area of the temporal lobe. And so
now if you're going to do a study where
you want to understand the temporal
lobe, you're not looking at millions of
neurons in the temporal loes
individually. you're looking at a whole
population. So that kind of idea of
understanding neuronal populations and
how they communicate with one another,
one is obviously much more efficient um
in the sense of you don't have to model
all of these individual neurons um and
then two the idea of do neurons who are
together kind of communicating that way
do they tend to have certain kinds of
behaviors or lead to larger emergent
behaviors from the the organism. So that
that's kind of what allows us to draw
out these sort of um these diagrams that
we've seen so far. It's like well why do
we only have five circles or variables?
Why don't we have a billion? Um that's
why uh in a sense.
So
um with
this chapter we quickly get into sort of
a lot of technical information.
This is what is known as a canonical m
cortical microcircuit as it's quite
obvious from looking at the chapter. Um
here the idea is there's communication
between these different kinds of
neuronal populations that might be able
to be located in certain areas of the
brain. For example, on the far left we
see that there's an attempt to sort of
map uh to these neuron populations to
different areas of the brain. the basil
ganglia secondary phalamus. Um
another um something that's that's quite
significant in uh sort of empirical
neuroscientific and neurobiological
studies is the idea of looking at um
pyramidal cells. Um so that we also have
different types of neurons right so they
don't all necessarily function
similarly. The main thing that I would
say anyone reading this chapter could
potentially take away whether they want
to really get into the fine details of
neurobi neurobiology or not. is that one
of the core kind of empirical findings
is that deep pyramidal cells, that's
what they're called, um that are kind of
uh deeper in the brain as it were, uh
send these projections or expectations
uh down to
superficial pyramidal cells that are
much closer to um the other end of the
layers here. uh that is ones that are
closer to sensory receptors. So you can
imagine like um if we had a spectrum or
or or kind of like this kind of layering
of these cortical layers, some of them
are much closer to your eyes so to
speak. That is your eyes taking in
visual information, sensory information.
It it will that information kind of hits
so to speak. it kind of touches on or is
received as an input at these kind of
more shallow layers and then as you go
um that then
go uh towards the deeper layers, right?
So you have this kind of communication
back and forth uh depending on depth,
right? So these superficial more shallow
layer neurons send prediction errors
deeper. Um so you have these bottom up
prediction errors. Then the deeper
neurons or layers send down these kind
of top down projections or predictions.
So what does that mean? Well, you can
think of someone who, you know, believes
that it's daytime right now and then
they step outside and they see that
there's no sun and they check the time
and it's midnight and they suddenly
realize, oh, it must not be daytime. it
must be nighttime. So they
kind of figuratively you could say that
at the deeper layers they had this
belief that it was daytime in fact but
then by receiving this incoming sensory
information
um you kind of had the the sensory
observation come into conflict with the
top down expectation or projection the
belief and then there was a correction
to that belief. Right? And so this is
sort of the this is sort of the arena of
belief as it were where where prediction
errors are identified sent uh deeper
into the sort of the layer uh deeper
into the cortical layer structure here
and then kind of meet with the the
expectations that were already there in
the brain and uh there's some kind of
presumably resolution that happens. How
does that happen through all of this
sort of message passing right? So you
have a belief that belief gets corrected
by sensory information. Um
so this is the the general sort of
scheme for that. But to for those who
are like why why do we have three
different um illustrations here? This is
simply like three different ways of kind
of communicating the same thing. Uh for
those who have already skipped ahead to
like chapters seven and eight recognize
the difference between discrete versus
continuous time models, uh the this
illustration to the far right will look
a little bit more familiar. We have our
S's for hidden states. We have our O's
for observations,
right? We have our our G uh whenever we
compute expected free energy per policy.
We have our A matrix for perception. Uh
our likelihood matrix. So you know the
that's what is it day or night those are
the hidden states s uh you know do I see
sunlight and do I see the time you know
being uh you know yes or no those are
observations it's in the a matrix that
they kind of touch uh there um yeah
Alexander go for it
>> um
so
this may just be me being very literal
with the terms because of the
neurobiology background But um based on
what you described about the cortical
layer and like the relationship between
the deep parameal and the superficial
parameal neurons um
it seems like and tell me if this is
correct or not. Um that the the
understanding of this circuit is that
the deep parameal neurons um are already
have a prediction or are already doing
a thing in in the brain. Um, and that
the incoming input
into layer 4 um
is able to update or sort of like
redirect, but even in the absence of
layer 4 input, they would still be doing
something.
>> Yes. submission.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think that I think that's
fair to say. Um yeah, it's it's in the
sense that so long as you have the
message passing occurring to use that
language or the the idea that these
neurons are in fact, you know, linked to
one another in some fashion and are
actively sending out signals. It's like,
you know, at no point, as far as I'm
aware, you I'm
uh I mean, I I personally don't have a
neurobiology background, so I'd almost
be willing to take your word on a few
aspects of this, but having spent a lot
of time with this chapter and and then
also the kind of the mathematical
formalisms and the rest like that, I am
strongly familiar with, it's like, yeah,
as long as message passing is occurring,
I mean, these neurons don't like kind of
shut down, right? I mean, they're
they're all sort of like living in a in
a continuously kind of living and and
operating brain. So, so yeah, that
that'd be right. Um, and it's it's it's
sort of like, you know, there's
communication from the superficial cells
to the deep, from the deep to the
superficial. And so there's this kind of
updating that happens between them,
right? They sort of meet in the middle
in different sorts of ways. Um so if one
is willing to accept the sort of
formalisms and and hypotheses of active
inference and the free energy principle
uh then then we would not only say that
this happens but we would actually say
that it happens in a particular way and
in that way would sort of look like
this. It would look like there are
prediction errors which is not unique to
active inference. Um it's rather that
there would be this kind of this kind of
basium uh basian paradigm that we're in
and you know a lot of the specific
functions and formulas and whenever we
look at you know the maths behind free
energy and expected free energy we from
a active inference standpoint we would
be saying like yes this is how that
happens. Um but it it's it seems pretty
uh widely accepted through many areas of
neuroscience. People who are you know
less interested in some of the things
that active inference looks at but um
you know those who look at uh dopamine
you know and are totally centered on on
neurobiology or neurotrans transmitters.
And it's kind of widely accepted that
dopamine encodes uh reward prediction
errors. And so this idea of there being
prediction errors kind of assumes that
there's something
already present and operating whether it
be beliefs or whatever word we want to
use there. um those are sort of already
functioning in the brain perhaps at the
deeper areas that the deeper uh parameal
cells and then with new sensory inputs
there's some kind of you know error that
happens between the beliefs that were
held versus the sensory information that
was received.
Um and one more question about um some
of the language. Uh you said at one
point that the projections from the
neurons um from one region to another
are like beliefs. Is that like a a a
metaphor or is that like literally how
to interpret um a kind of circuit?
is that um the existence of connections
or message passing is the propagation of
a belief.
>> I see. Yeah. Yeah. It's
it's kind of like yes to everything. Um
I would say so unfortunately the
textbook kind of switches around a
little bit with the terminology which is
why even mids sentence I'm like
projections expectations like before I
continue um like as far as mathematical
formalisms go like here this this middle
one is for the the continuous case so
it's just it's very
like looking at this from a mathematical
perspective this mu here refers to an um
ultimately like an average or or an
expectation in the mathematical sense.
Um and so that that term can be like
very reasonably accurately used here
like an expectation. Um a projection is
a fair term to use which has also been
used in the textbook at certain points.
Um projection kind of implies that. Um,
but it also implies like that, you know,
some kind of movement or pushing like
we're we're not we don't just have this
expectation but we're moving it is does
that mean we're moving it as a message
to these other cortical layers or does
it mean that you know it's being
projected into the future like this is
what I expect will happen in the future
little ambiguous both of them could be
reasonably said to be uh valid here
though and then as far as calling it a
belief. Um, that's a bit tricky too in
the sense that I would certainly not say
belief in a kind of colloquial everyday
sense of like we can explicitly,
you know, quote unquote rationally talk
about what our beliefs are. Like I
believe, you know, such and such like
I'm not sure if my arm believes that
it's exactly here or exactly there, but
there's something going on to where it
like my brain is locating where my arm
is. uh you know so that the idea of like
you know many of these processes are are
largely unconscious so I I wouldn't say
that um you know belief in a very
everyday kind of sense but um given that
this expectation is coming from a place
that you know hasn't even necessarily
received sensory input yet on the
current situation in a sense it is like
a belief um and then finally like belief
propagation as a mathematical formalism.
Um, in that case, it's just we're just
kind of moving these numbers around.
We're taking a an expectation, an
average, and we're we're kind of pushing
it as a message to, you know, some other
structure that will then do something
with that. Use it to compute its own
average or something. So, kind of like
playing telephone. Um, I hope that was
useful. I'm sorry that I couldn't give
like a more like like precise answer,
but it's just uh yeah, it's a big
picture.
Cool.
Um
yeah, that's
again this is just another way of kind
of formalizing the figure we already
saw. It's just kind of drawing it from
left to right. um in the sense that you
know there are there's communication
sort of vertically and horizontally as
it were um between these neuronal
populations. So we can see there there's
descending prediction error. There's us
uh excuse me descending predictions and
ascending prediction errors like I
already mentioned. Um and then you can
see the communication between
specifically like deep and superficial.
um for sake of time I'll I'll just say
that this is a kind of another way of of
representing that um and then
uh motor commands. So they they they you
know not everyone who comes in active
inference is specifically interested in
say proprioception.
uh like as as we might be familiar with
by now at this point in the textbook,
there's sort of three different uh forms
of of of inference that can occur uh or
or sensory data that can be collected
that being extterosceptive that is
what's from outside of the agent or
organism uh you know so that that would
relate most commonly to the five senses
what I see what I touch what I feel um
externally um then there's
interosceptive which would be the the
body's ability to sort of read itself
internally. So what does it mean for the
brain whenever it notices that its heart
rate has you know risen and uh you know
its stomach is growling and uh you know
these sort of internal signals that are
received um that we don't use our eyes
and our outer like dermal like our skin
to feel and uh you know the other five
senses that we usually think of as you
know receiving in information from the
outside. Then there's proprioception
which largely just has to do with
movement um generally kind of motor
commands. Um they don't they they tend
to be kind of distinguished in that they
they have to do a lot more with sort of
um reflex arcs. They have to do with how
you know how does um the forearm rotate
on its joint. um how does it do that in
a way that you know can can um sort of
be inferred so that the organism can
actually move its body and its joints in
a way that it wants to whether
consciously unconsciously or otherwise
um most importantly I think here is that
we're looking at this notion of like
okay in order for my hand to go from
point A to point B or like from a
resting state to picking up my glass so
that I can drink my water. Um, a lot of
inference sort of needs to to happen,
right, to get from point A to point B.
Um, there's a lot of prediction error
that needs to be sort of um, computed
and then through action overcome. It's
like, well, if I want to pick up my
water, but my hand is over here in a
resting state, I'm already at a a pretty
strong prediction error uh, relative to
this preference or desire that I have
for picking up the glass of water,
right? So, I need to kind of minimize
that. Uh, presumably by moving my hand
closer and closer to picking up the
glass of water. Um, that means I have to
move my arm. That means I have to engage
the the muscles in my arm in order to
like actually move it. Um, so there's
just sort of a variety of processes here
that are occurring down to like a rather
micro sort of level. Um, and this is one
way of attempting to sort of communicate
how that occurs in the formalisms of
active inference where we do have these
these descending expectations or
projections or beliefs. Um and then we
have
uh through the mo motor neurons and like
actual interaction with the reality of
of receiving the proprioceptive inputs.
they have a prediction error that can
then be computed from the incoming
observations that are received and then
they attempt to sort of map this to
neurobiological coralates by placing it
on top of this um sort of implicit
diagram with the dorsal and ventral
horns
subcortical structures. This is I they
go most deeply into talking about action
here. Um kind of the the basil ganglia
circuit in its relationship to neuronal
message passing. Again, this is um this
is kind of like being able to say like,
okay, well, we have we have this whole
kind of reactive style active inference.
We're we're minimizing variational free
energy. um we we we try to increase
accuracy of our model. We try to reduce
complexity. Um but then why is it that
we have expected free energy and
expected you know energy of the future?
Um and the idea of having goals and
trying to accomplish goals and so on.
And so this kind of gives a little bit
more, you know, biological evidence to
that and that we we we have references
to um you know, sort of how the brain
decides to take on particular actions
not just to uh increase accuracy and
reduce complexity of its model, but also
uh and in tandem sort of with that to
achieve um goals.
And then
these are just further ways of kind of
talking about that because action uh can
actually be sort of divided up whenever
you get deeper. There's a really nice
concise
u formalism
for action or policy inference and
active inference that I've really
enjoyed showing during like talks I've
given on these things um that
unfortunately they don't have in this
book. Uh it's it's used throughout
probably 90% of all the simulations that
this book refers to. It's used in the
SPM library, the PIMDP library, RX and
uh I'm not sure it was RX infer but many
of these other libraries. Um but
essentially it
the policy inference boils down to um
sort of computing expected free energy
to which relates to kind of like
deliberate decision making or trying to
achieve particular goals like oh I'm
moving my hand so that I can pick up you
know this glass of water so that I can
drink it. um and that that relates to
these sort of direct pathways
um along the the the ganglen circuitry
here. Meanwhile, um we also have habits,
right? Uh which in a colloquial sense
many people are familiar with. Um you
know, whether it be a sort of a bad
habit, chewing fingernails, smoking, uh
you know, a cigarette, uh or otherwise.
Um or just kind of, you know, habitual
ticks or, you know, knocking on wood,
whether you believe in the idea of doing
that or not, but you've done it so many
times that you can't help but not do it.
Um so that the the idea of having habits
that you know in the in the formalism
here it's kind of just through
repetition one builds up a habit. Um and
then whenever it comes to sort of neurom
modulation and neurotransmission,
uh whenever someone is not the the
hypothesis here is that whenever someone
is not terribly confident in their
ability to take actions that will
successfully lead to accomplishing their
goals, whether it be picking up the
glass of water or it be making some
major, you know, financial decision. for
their livelihood and their their future
or whatever it be. Um, when lacking
confidence, um, there's kind of an
activation of other areas of the brain
that relate to habits, which would sort
of be like contextfree
policies or actions. It's like, oh,
whenever I don't know what to do, this
is what I do. Um, unconsciously, not not
whatsoever necessarily meaning that
you're, you know, consciously doing
this. Um so that gives us E which is a
prior on policies or a prior on actions.
So you can also think of that in a sense
is like um you know itself being a sort
of expectation of what to do regardless
of circumstance.
um with some of my my computational
psychiatry work that I've been doing
with a a group at the institute recently
um like one way of viewing an individual
who you know unfortunately has been
through some form of um trauma or
struggles perhaps with certain uh kind
of kinds or veillances of anxiety. Um it
can be the case that over a very
significant amount of time whenever
someone is struggling with those kinds
of um um symptoms as it were uh they
they tend towards kind of avoidant
behaviors in order to avoid uh
triggering or or uh otherwise
anxietyinducing situations.
And there's an interesting hypothesis
there that by doing that more and more
even as someone continues to you know
say take a prescribed medication seek
additional care practice emo emotional
regulation strategies see a therapist or
otherwise once that habit is built up
strongly enough uh one can become very
used to kind of engaging in those
avoidant behavior behaviors um despite
doing otherwise overall like really well
um you mentally with their health. And
so
it's it's tough to break habits. In
order to kind of break a habit, the
hypothesis here would be that you would
need to repeatedly engage with something
that is mutually exclusive to the the
habit, right? Um, so we can think of
someone who who has been smoking, you
know, cigarettes for a very long time or
something. It's like in order to quit
once you get past the the the chemical
addiction, um, you would need to
repeatedly not smoke in order to also
relieve this sort of mental habit that
this this the activation of this
indirect pathway that says, "Oh, I'm not
sure what to do or maybe I'm stressed. I
will go smoke a cigarette." is a
contextfree you know way of dealing with
this situation you know whether is it
the morning you can smoke is it the
afternoon you can smoke is it the
evening you can smoke that's the sense
of the context for am I on break right
now I can smoke like right so that's um
it it says a lot about animal behavior
too right because whenever we we
consider the idea of like oh you know
animals including human infants being
born with different kinds of like sort
of emergent behaviors that we frequently
see despite that the the the child or
the the infant or the animal never
actually being taught how to um do those
things or being taught to you know an
infant not being taught to cry rather
they tend to do it on their own. Um it's
sort of like we could almost formalize
that as a kind of ingrained habit that
that sort of pre-exists.
Um well, it's through repetitions of of
action and turning perception that
perhaps a baby eventually learns to move
from the crying to an alternative which
might be using you know language once
they hit a certain age or and are able
to to articulate themselves and you know
kind of perceive that there's a meaning
between this the the sounds of certain
words or certain sounds and them having
a reference. of
saying you're hungry means something um
to your to your parent. Uh right. So um
with
all of that with talking now about sort
of neurom modulation and transmission
the idea of confidence um whenever I
used the word confidence earlier um
there's sort of technical formalism of
that here is expected policy precision.
Um essentially when we think of
neurotransmitters whether you're an
active inference or not we tend to view
them as they have an impact they they
modulate
um communication between neurons. So
that would mean that they'd have a
direct impact on
these message passing schemes that are
going on in the brain. um most simply we
could consider them as sort of um
amplifying or or sort of dampening
different signals. Um so whenever we
think of uh a likelihood we could say
you know one's um belief in seeing the
sun that means it's daytime. Uh they
don't see any sunlight that means it's
nighttime. You could say that they have
that as a sort of 2x two matrix. Um you
know it's it's probability of sun goes
to day is a 1.0. That means you're
completely certain of that. Um and then
the opposite you don't see the sunlight
it must be daytime. That's a 1.0 right
and with with probability summing to one
that means that seeing the sun and it
being nighttime has a probability of
zero. 1 - 0 is one everything sums to
one and vice versa. Um if we reduce the
precision on that likelihood
uh on that overall matrix say to
then what happens is that now I now it's
as if I believe that if I see the sun
there's about a 3/4 of probability that
it's that it's daytime and then a one
quarter probability that oh no actually
I'm seeing the sun and it's night like
is it unlikely Sure. But is it like
impossible according to my new downtuned
likelihood matrix? No. It's a it's about
you know 0.25 probable. Um so that's
sort of the the notion of precision and
it that becomes really significant in a
lot of different kinds of cognitive
phenomena. Um for example, whenever it
comes to the study of sort of
hallucination and delusion, um it might
be the case that you could formalize
that as there's reduced precision on
between what one believes and what one
sees. You know, that is between one's
inferred hidden states of the world
versus the sensory observations that are
actually uh received. um by down tuning
that precision it's almost like you're
saying oh I'm less certain that what I'm
seeing matches up with what I would you
know believe or I'm I'm it it's it's
more difficult to say right like what
would happen if we just go back to the
simplified example I gave a moment ago
of the 2x2 matrix and say oh if I see
the sunlight it's a.5 probability that
it's daytime probabilities sum to one so
that would mean that the probability of
it being nighttime time would also be
0.5. So that means I literally I see the
sunlight, but based on my likelihood
matrix being downtuned to precision of
0.5,
what's happening is I have no idea if
this me seeing the sun means it's day or
night. It's no longer a useful sensory
signal. That's clear. It's like this
isn't telling me to think one way or the
other. Now, um that that could lead to
some some major major issues, right? Not
just for someone trying to figure out if
it's day or night time, which already
has its own issues. If you're trying to
determine like is a sort of horistic
like, oh, do I should I be sleeping or
should I be getting ready to go to work?
Um is it day or night? I just woke up.
Uh but it could also be, you know, for
for much higher stake situations, right?
to have to kind of have a downtuned um
you know understanding of the world and
and it opens up doors for potential like
many to many mappings uh to where it's
very difficult to sort of parse through
what different things mean and being
able to actually use sensory information
in any kind of useful way for for
navigating the world. Um and it's there
that you know the you know um delusion
is a is a general sense of you know
despite receiving particular kinds of
evidence that maybe an external observer
might say oh yeah no if you see the
sunlight it should definitely lead you
to infer that it's daytime. Um you know
the the person might still be uncertain
nonetheless.
So with this table here which I've
always found rather interesting although
much of this you know they use the word
puditive roles of neurotransmitters
uh but but the main point here is that
these are these are hypotheses regarding
are there particular neurotransmitters
that can onetoone be linked up with the
precisions on these different components
in a model. um we've been loosely
introduced in the preceding chapters and
much more strongly we'll see them in in
play in chapters 7 and 8 in the se
second half of the book. Um, but the
idea that that aceticoline
could be what modulates
the precision on likelihood, which is
kind of what I'm talking about the the
relationship between observations and
hidden states. Um, hidden state
transitions, which would be, you know,
um, day goes to night and night goes to
day. um day going to day is very unl you
know virtually unlikely if we view this
in you know a certain interval and so so
having beliefs
unconsciously or not uh about how hidden
states themselves transition or how they
transition conditioned on action which
is also how we most often see this an
act of inference such as oh if you're
hungry uh you have a belief that you if
you eat food then you'll go from hungry
to sated right? You're using an action
to hit change or transition in the state
of the world. Nor adrenaline
um here based on just this kind of
handful of study maybe a little bit more
than a handful but but several studies
um you know kind of point at this idea
that the noradrenaline or norepinephrine
could have a relationship with one's
perception of how um essentially the
environment changes or hidden states of
the world change. um that comes up very
strongly in psychiatry as well. um you
know with uh my own research it's like a
general finding is that individuals um
with with PTSD uh tend to have kind of
aberrant um uh functioning of of in
production of norepinephrine and
noradrenaline uh in the brain that can
lead to a perception of the environment
being very volatile whenever it isn't.
Uh, put simply like someone
having uncertainty if at any moment the
hidden state of the world can go from
I'm safe to I'm in danger. Um, on
average those who don't have kind of the
symptomatology of PTSD
um tend to assume if they're in a safe
situation it will continue to be safe
more or less on average. Maybe not
perfectly onetoone uh which is probably
for the best uh just in case something
does come up but on average you're not
it's it's not a volatile belief of oh
dramatically it will within a blip of a
moment change from a safe to unsafe
situation um with PTSD it can be
different right so transitions or the
idea of having um sort of a precision on
trans transitions in these models that's
relatable to neurotrans transmission um
brings up a lot of implications for
thinking about things like
pharmarmacology or at least just the
brain functioning in general whether
you're intending to study like medical
treatments or not. Um dopamine and
policies this is actually there's much
more sort of evidence for this. A
classic study was shortened back with
Frista and others in 2014 and I briefly
mentioned like dopamine being related to
reward prediction errors earlier. um
this this is kind of like a little bit
more broadly accepted certainly within
the active inference and uh literature.
I'm not sure about the entirety of
neuroscience, but that many others are
are willing to kind of accept this sort
of relationship here. Um this relates to
sort of the um a colloquial word would
be confidence here of saying like do you
have confidence in your ability to
choose actions or policies that will
lead to kind of accomplishing what it is
you're trying to to accomplish. Um that
would kind of be a relationship to to
dopamine. And you know a lot of people
think of this as like a sense of reward.
Um granted like excessive dopamine uh in
the re-uptake system can actually lead
to uh very you know on the opposite end
rather problematic things such as um you
know kind of hyperactivation of the the
dopamineergic system can lead someone to
have rather grandiose sort of delusional
beliefs um as well. So it's it's um it's
found in uh schizophrenia for example,
which is not to say that everyone who
has schizophrenia is necessarily, you
know, happy. This isn't to put a
positive veilance on. It's just to say
like they're they're interesting
behaviors that happen with too much or
too little uh of of these kinds of um
quantities and serotonin um very
commonly used in pharmarmacology, SSRIs
and so on. um relating to, you know,
potentially being the parameters on
preferences or specifically
interosceptive likelihood. Um I'm
probably spending too much time on that,
but um this it's just
>> they're essentially trying to map the
brain. So yeah, go ahead, Alexander. I'm
sorry I've been talking a long time.
>> No, it's okay. Um it's just uh
obviously that figure table's adapted
from a paper. Um, but it's just uh
I don't know what it is about
neuroscience. Um, but that is such a
classic table of just like we tried to
collect all of the evidence and put it
in one place like these are the facts.
um even if they the evidence can seem
quite disperate like it's found in this
region or it's like linked to this
experiment or it's related to this thing
and it's like it's not obvious why those
pieces of evidence all build a coherent
story to support that um
neurotransmitter story. And so I just
like I I too have made tables like this
about you know a specific
>> protein or protein receptor and like
just trying to um yeah figure out how to
uh repres represent data um and organize
kind of the facts uh to build a case for
um linking these together. But that is
really cool that the neurotransmitters
can be linked to
um these specific components of the
generative model.
>> Sure.
Yeah. Yeah. No, I I'm very with you on
that. It's, you know, I appreciate that
they put the word puditive here. That is
like it, this is a very top down like,
well, if there were a trans
neurotransmitter that could be said to
link up to, you know, a component of the
model, this is probably what it would
be, you know, based on this evidence
that may or may not perfectly support
the claim, but kind of points to it. So,
what what I mean is it's like you they
are kind of just
this could be seen as an attempt to just
fill out this table. Um, yeah, it's I
mean
this is rather significant, you know,
research that's been done. I don't know
if everyone on the author list in this
group, well, okay, that dopamine is a
bad example, but nor adrenaline. I don't
know if every author here is going to
look at this table and then say, "Oh,
yes, this is, you know, this is what
we're going for. This is what we were
trying to do." It's like, um, you know,
certain people were trying to study iss
um, you know, those who work in
pharmarmacology, I think, would be
especially interested in this and also
probably hope that you could, um, kind
of do a onetoone
um mapping of a neurotransmitter to a
transition because uh to a precision
rather um because it's like you know in
that in there's a you know I've been
going over this paper on schizophrenia
recently for example that is from an
active inference perspective or
framework and so they make a model you
know of a of a hypothetical person and
so this um this person like is pl is
engaging in a behavioral task like trial
by trial and we can simulate how that
works and kind of how the task works and
then along the way they simulate this
would be the impact of using you know an
SSRI
and how it would change their behavior.
And so if you could come up with certain
kinds of behavioral criteria to say
like, oh, here is a person with
schizophrenia playing this game and and
we get to observe them playing the game
and then determine here the problematic
things that happened. You know, they
they thought they chose one color for a
card and then it was actually a
different one. They hallucinated. This
sort of thing. you come up with all
these criteria and then then you can
create an artificial intervention by
giving you know having this artificial
person take an SSRI and then looking at
like if it's if this is true then that
means that the impact on the precision
there in the model will lead to a a more
normative normal behavior of them
playing the game and clearly
has has mitigated a lot of the sort of
delusional or a delusion producing sort
of symptoms in the model. And so at the
end of the day we get to you know the
idea would be to get into like precision
pharmarmacology by making a purely
incilico like artificial simulation
there right and it's so if you could
very strongly prove these sorts of
things down to the degree that you could
not just look at like oh is this
medication going to be helpful? Yes or
no? But also like how much do we need to
impact the precision in the model? How
much do we you know then you could
really you could really fine-tune these
kinds of things and maybe even fine-tune
them like to each individual know
exactly what dosage of what specific
like chemical composition in a in a
treatment would need to be. Um I love
the idea of all of that. I think it's I
think it's very like cool or fascinating
and then I thought I think also for
those who you know would prefer some
kind of like pharmarmacology based
treatment or see that as one of the few
options available to them like yeah uh
more precision is better uh more
precision of our understanding about
those things. That said, like all of
these need to be all of these need to be
tested more thoroughly. And yeah, to be
able to make any broad statement based
on this table, it's like I think the
textbook authors were just trying to
just kind of consolidate what they what
they had to try and um you know, I I I
think I think this is great for
researchers who are like, "Oh, I would
like to test this." It's like does does
serotonin
if we if we collect enough behavioral
data or neuro neuroiming data or both um
and then we look at people who you know
are having their serotonin reuptake
system modulated or not or being given a
particular treatment like do we see the
model that we fit to their behavior like
does something happen with their
preferences matrix from there or does
something happen to the precision on you
know their body's ability to read
itself. If it does, then maybe you do
have more evidence for this kind of
claim. Um,
yeah, I I just I come back to this very
often because I find it fascinating, but
I'm always like
I just need more
validation. And I'm sure the authors
themselves will probably agree. Um,
yeah. And then this this final figure
5.5 is just like
sort of trying to
and this is how I describe this to to
social scientists who are interested in
these things but don't have any
particular like strong background or
potentially even interest in like fine
details of neuroscience. But just the
idea of being able to say like if we can
map these more generally understood or
at least we agree on generally like
their definitions in social science of
what it means to plan something or to
act to have a goal versus just engage in
a habit, what it means to, you know,
have beliefs or predict something. like
it's sort of um
and then also for people who want to do
any kind of cognitive modeling or or
even people who don't want to do
cognitive modeling but they just want to
do something very hardcore um sort of
robotics driven or they're trying to
model an organism or something. It's
like well with active inference as a
framework you do if you engage in
building these kinds of models you do
get the ability to sort of like pinpoint
as opposed to working with a total
blackbox model of you know a billion
parameters none of which we know exactly
what they do or what they're for. um
we're now able to say like oh whenever
we look inside this model we do see the
coralates of habits and here's why the
the agent made this decision and we can
look at the balance between how it
evaluated you know it's its hypothetical
brain evaluated its habits versus its
goals and how it weighed uh certain
actions based on the information gain
that it thought it would get from doing
something versus the the pragmatic value
it thought it would get and um so
there's just there's just a lot more
sort of interpretability um to these
models. So from a modeler's perspective,
my perspective as a computational
modeler, like I would love for this to
be even like 80%, you know, true more or
less. Like it would be wonderful to have
a reasonable
model that is that interpretable to
where you could even go to someone who
doesn't understand any of this and use
kind of more a everyday action uh uh
excuse me everyday language to say like
oh well the the robot was planning to do
this because it had these particular
habits and you know it had these goals
and this is how it made that decision.
And so for those who are interested in
things like um AI and making those like
AIdriven systems to where you can
actually audit the behavior of those
kinds of u agents or robots or otherwise
um I think that that could have a lot of
sort of significant value. I think what
what others are you know afraid of is a
sort of you know robots start making
decisions without us really knowing or
understanding why. Which means that one
that leads to a lot of unpredictability
on our end like what are these things
going to do and then two it really harms
our ability to finetune the the AI or
the robots because we don't know exactly
how to adjust those billion parameters
that they have right in a reasonable way
that is interpretable. Um so
yeah
and that concludes the
first half of the active inference
textbook and uh thank you all for
joining. I uh I think I talked a little
much on this one, but uh it's just uh
there's a lot going on in this chapter
and there's so many different ways and
connections uh when when describing it
or looking at it. Um so next week at the
same time uh we'll jump back to cohort 8
and kind of wrap up the textbook um
chapter 10 and uh and
uh and Daniel will be will be doing the
the morning session for that. Um he and
I were going to do something different
for this textbook reading session where
we're going to talk more about
applications of active inference and
maybe even look at some actual code. Um
but we know that
uh one our symposium is coming up so we
we weren't able to coordinate on that
like terribly well given the amount of
time that we had available. Um but uh
more importantly we're very excited for
uh Sanjieve Namoshi's
textbook on active inference coming out
early next year and so we're actually
more ready to start talking about code
whenever that comes out. Um, this
textbook lends itself well to talking
about mat lab code. Not everyone who
attends the textbook is ready to pay for
proprietary software and learn it. Um,
but Sanji Nam Jooshi's textbook will
have accompanying code that I believe
will all be open source uh largely in
Python. Um hopefully today me talking a
little bit about pharmarmacology and
trying to model psychiatric disorders
counts as an application. I think it
does. But uh yeah, so anyway um thank
you so much folks for for attending. Um
appreciate you. We'll see you at the
next one.
Take care.
>> Thank you. Thanks.